I just lectures on chaos
engineering for cloud architecture.
So we really need to look at why
we need to do chaos engineering.
This really actually goes all the way back
to, the automotive industry
back in the 1960s and 70s
on, reliability and things like that.
We need to take some of those same
Six Sigma practices that were formed
in Japanese car companies and apply them
to cloud architectures, because,
they are complex
and we cannot rely on cloud
service providers to provide,
you know, even four nines uptime.
We're not even at two nights uptime
right now.
So we've got to come up
with a better way of handling
and testing the resiliency of our systems.
So a great, great example.
Just recently we've had back to back weeks
of AWS outage in the eastern region,
which has caused mass chaos
for a lot of organizations.
So if I were to do my chaos engineering
upfront, I would have, figured out,
what experiments I could
do to see
if these sorts of things would happen.
How would my system stand up,
which, finds holes and gaps in my,
architecture
that I can improve on and make better?
And there are some design patterns
we're going to talk about
that can be leveraged in some of these.
So let's dive right in.
So first off, what is chaos engineering.
It's a discipline
of experimenting a system
to build confidence in that system.
So it's things like, in the olden days
when you had your own data center walking
by a rack of machines and pulling the plug
and seeing what happens to your system.
Does a whole company come down about
you really don't want to do that, right?
So we got to do this
in, controlled conditions.
So not affecting, production.
That's the key behind it, right?
So controlled data driven, data
driven experiments.
This should be part of your test suite.
When you go into production.
And you should be continuously
testing, testing these,
these scenarios that you come up with.
So the whole idea is
you come up with a hypothesis,
you have a controlled environment
you want to test
in that controlled environment
and then improve your architectures.
You need to.
Okay. So,
why do we want it in the cloud
specifically?
Well, because you don't have complete
control over the cloud.
This really goes into something
that happened with the personal listening
device,
also known in the 1980s as the Walkman.
A lot of people think that Sony
actually created the Walkman.
Actually, they did not.
The personal cassette, recorder
or player was actually created by RCA.
And RCA had a really,
really killer, product,
but it was expensive
and it failed sometimes.
And the reason
why is they focus on the individual
components of that RCA player.
They focus on just the individual
components being the highest quality
possible.
So they put very expensive,
high quality parts into them.
Sony took a different approach.
Sony said, hey,
I know there's going to be failures.
How can I still operate and be resilient
even if there are failures
in individual components?
We need to take that same philosophy,
especially in the cloud environment
where there will be failures.
We have to assume that services
are going to go down.
So how do we handle that?
How do we understand the coupling
between the different services
so that we can understand
hey, I need redundancy here.
I don't care, I have, dependencies.
I've got coupling here
that I didn't understand.
I need to understand
so I can reroute, traffic if I need to,
or I can, I can I, fail gracefully
without master catastrophe, right?
Cost of, downtime.
And this is average
across, across industries.
It's greater in some industries.
Another is about, $5,000.
Almost $6,000
a minute of unplanned, outage.
And it's even worse when you talk about,
you know, Black Friday sales or Cyber
Monday
sales, where your e-commerce
site needs to be up and running.
Right. This could be massive.
So let's talk about the four steps
of chaos engineering, process.
First, define
what your steady state looks like.
You've got to know what that is.
If you can't,
then you can't form a hypothesis.
And your hypothesis should be
if something happens,
this is how I should react,
or my system should react this way.
That's your hypothesis.
Then you want to run a controlled
experiment against that hypothesis.
If something happens,
what are my end results?
Did it meet what my expectations were?
You observe, you learn.
You have a feedback loop to improve.
You make adjustments to your, architecture
many times.
Believe it or not, many times
you know how to change a line of code.
Many times it's, the way
that you've configured your services.
It could be, there's
lots of different design patterns
we're going to talk about on
how do I handle failure gracefully.
Right.
Notifying the user,
oh, your transaction did not go through.
Please try again.
We've all seen it, right?
That's better than just sitting there
and spinning and not knowing what to do.
So you've got to come up
with your steady state, your hypothesis,
what your is going to test,
and then make improvements.
All right.
So different failure modes and mitigations
that we can talk about.
Failure modes a VMware
or container goes away.
It gets killed right.
Real world impact is abrupt capacity drop.
All of a sudden I was handling a thousand,
concurrent, transactions.
Now I can only handle 100.
That would be really bad, right?
What do I do about that?
Well, if it's gracefully shut down
and retries, that's.
That's something you could do.
What if I have network
latency problems, which happen a lot,
especially in the cloud, where,
you've got noisy neighbors
that are consuming a lot of, network.
Or even if you're in, in your own data
center,
your network
connectivity to your data center
may be compromised in some way,
and you may have decreased latency.
A lot of people,
what they do is they have multiple,
ISPs and internet service providers
coming into their data center.
Right.
Making sure that, hey,
if one of them goes down, I have a backup.
Right.
It depends on your mission
criticality, right?
Real world impact.
I get timeouts, I get requests
blocking, and everything get clogged up.
That could be a cascading failure
in a lot of cases.
Best way to handle
this is circuit breaker and timeout.
Design patterns.
All right.
Let's talk about resource
exhaustion. Right.
All of a sudden, I get CPU spikes.
Maybe I'm using
all the resources in a pod.
What do I do?
I this is where autoscaling,
observability
that we've talked about in other lectures.
I can see what's going on
on my individual pod, on my individual
device, and I can I can make,
a, autoscale to another pod
or another container or whatever
the case may be.
Dependency downtime.
This we're seeing consistently
in the major outages in the cloud service
providers.
Azure's had an outage, big outage
recently at AWS.
Two, weekly back to back outages,
all on dependency downtime.
Every single
one of them was dependency downtime.
So which caused cascading failures.
And I'm going to talk
specifically about one of them.
But this is where you use bulkheads
and asynchronous comms.
Right.
So hey, I send something
I'm not completely blocked.
Async.
I mean, I may not get the, answer back,
but I can still run in some capacity.
And then also, let's look at zone
and regional outages.
Right.
I've got a whole zone,
us East one out twice in two weeks.
Right. For AWS.
What do I do about that?
I need to have a multi-region failover,
or even multi-cloud failover
that's even even more secure or reliable.
Unnecessarily secure.
You got a whole security issue
you got to deal with.
All right, let's talk about auto recovery
design pattern.
Right. Really simple.
A pod dies, a container dies.
I spin up a new pod, new containers.
I have a recovery event, and then,
hey, it worked.
That's my first experiment.
Hey, I kill a pod.
It starts up simple experiment.
This is a great design pattern to use.
And very simple to do.
Kubernetes has a built in Docker
swarm has it built in,
and there's a lot of other tools out there
that can, you can rely on
to, to do this effectively,
but keep.
Well, well and we'll talk about it.
All right.
Then there's the next one called Blast
Radius where we'll get to this.
So blast radius is hey,
I know if this service goes down
what the impact is going to be.
So in your hypothesis
you're going to state
if I take this service out,
these are the other services
that could be affected
or maybe not affected.
Run your experiment. See what happens.
If it's more than what you expected,
then you have a undocumented
coupling or dependency
between that service and other services.
Something you need to really watch out
for, right?
So you need to be cognizant of that.
So blast radius
great design pattern to look at.
All right.
Circuit breaker
this one's a simple one as well.
Very easy to implement.
And a lot of people forget about it
and they don't do it.
A great example here is I've got a
I'm charging
your, your bank account, your card,
your credit card payment gateway.
Right.
I, I send in a request to charge $100.
I get a success back. That's good.
What if I don't get a response back?
How long am I going to sit and wait?
This is where a circuit breaker comes
in. At a time.
Now I've gone beyond the threshold.
Stop.
Right. Retry.
Right?
Or throw an alert,
which we'll talk about in observability.
So don't sit forever on timeouts
that will block you
and you're not giving the user
any feedback that,
they may keep hitting the button and now
they've charged you or five, six times.
Right. So you got to be careful.
That sort of stuff.
All right.
Observability we've talked about there's
there's two lectures on observability
but really simple.
Your microservices are giving telemetry
to a tool
like Prometheus
which is an aggregator of telemetry,
which then can send alerts out
to an alert manager
or to Grafana to, to do like a gateway
or a dashboard for you.
Right.
So the idea here is that
I am giving telemetry into the system.
How can I leverage this in my experiments?
This is critical
for your experiments, right?
This gives me the visibility
into what's going on
when you do your experiment, instead of it
just being, an on and off switch,
I can actually see what has been affected
by taking out a service
like a blast radius.
I take out a service, I'm observing
what's going on.
I could see load increasing,
I could see a retries, going on, whatever
the case may be, and I can be alerted
and I can watch it in the dashboards.
Great. Serving all these, critical.
All right.
Multi-region, resiliency.
This one's a really important one.
And I've seen people fall
all over the place on this one.
Right.
This is where I'm using a DNS,
for example,
that, I can swap between.
Let's say that I'm going to, pagerduty.
Right. That's my that's one of my domains
paid.
And I get paid for that
I but the server's down, right?
That cloud region is down. Oh, no.
What do I do? I'm down completely.
Well, in the DNS,
I can change the record in the DNS.
I have waited a DNS.
I don't even need to change record.
A lot of times,
and it will fall back to my secondary.
Now, this happened
just recently in a major cloud service
provider outage.
They were running the DNS in the region.
They went down
as bad, right?
Ideally you'd want your DNS
even outside the cloud service provider.
I using a different cloud
service provider.
I spreading you know, the blast
radius spreading
that DNS outside of the blast radius
where where something happens
when that happens,
if your DNS is in the region
that, you're that goes down now,
you can't switch to another region easily.
And that's,
that's basically what happened.
Had a cascading failure.
So if you are setting a multi-region
resiliency, make sure you understand
that any services that you have
that you might be using, like a DNS
or load balancer or whatever you're using
to your multi-region resilience
that you're not have, that you don't have
an unintentional coupling
with that region.
All right.
So you've got to you've got to understand
your architecture completely.
All right.
Let's look at some of the tools out there.
There's some great tools out there
that help you do chaos.
Engineering chaos monkey from Netflix
Netflix
probably has one of the most resilient,
architectures,
cloud architectures out there.
And the reason
why is they went through a catastrophe.
Catastrophe.
They were down for like a day and a half,
over a decade ago.
And what they did was brilliant.
They stepped back and looked at their full
system architecture and said,
what are we doing?
Where are dependencies?
What's going on with our full system
architecture?
How can I have failure and still provide
service to people much like what Sony did?
They step back, took a look at it
systemically.
Right.
So they they've got great tools
to help you test.
For this type of stuff.
Great tool called Chaos Monkey.
You can check that one out.
Gremlin is another great tool.
It's a file library
that you can use. It's got
arbok built in,
which is your, your,
access control, right.
Role based access control.
And then litmus chaos for native,
Kubernetes, Crud, activities.
And then the cloud service providers
actually provide, some things like AWS
PhysX, Azure Chaos Studio,
GCP Resiliency Toolkit.
They offer some of these things as well,
which in some of their cases,
I wish they would use more on themselves.
Right.
Because, we've seen several outages
this year alone in 2025.
And I hope that,
we can improve, the industry overall.
All right.
How do you
how do I, design an effective experiment?
First off, don't do this in production
bad, right.
Don't do this in production. Right.
Do this in a selected environment.
In dev, in a product, in a Canary product.
You know, environment, right?
Where I'm
running a full test environment that looks
just like my production environment.
Do it
there. Right. Don't do it in production.
Look at my scope in my blast radius.
What am I going to experiment?
If you want to experiment,
the whole thing is probably too much.
You're not going to understand the cause
and effect of of what you just did.
So scope it down is as closely as you can
so that you can make adjustments
to your architecture,
make sure that you have observability in
there, or instrumentation and monitoring,
and make sure that you have aborts,
switches and timeouts.
Set so that you don't bring down
maybe your whole, canary environment.
Right. That wouldn't that wouldn't
give you any benefits. Right.
And document, document, document
everything that's going on.
If you're using an edge in AI to help you,
write these things and to analyze things,
make sure you're capturing all of that,
putting that into a nice rag,
or a file system
so that you can use the knowledge
from that
in a continuous improvement
in with your gin eye or with your team.
Okay.
Let's talk about some real world, case
studies, e-commerce case study,
huge, huge, huge.
Ones that are out there,
because of major outages and cloud
service providers on Cyber Monday
and Black Friday.
Right.
So slow.
Check out at peak.
This is a common problem experiment.
Here's an easy experiment
200 milliseconds latency
to inventory the, toxic proxy or whatever
it is.
Right.
And then my outcome
I'm expecting is a 95%, fallback to cache.
And then what am I going to do
to make sure that this happens?
Added circuit breaker and retry logic.
So there's my fix.
There's, you know, the outcome that I had.
So there you go.
You can write these things down right.
What your what you're testing for.
Here's another one on video streaming.
Database failover crashing
by buffering master database crash.
And in staging this would be catastrophic.
What am I going to do to to fix that?
These are the sorts of things that we want
to capture in, your, experiments.
All right.
This is not just an engineering test.
This is an organizational, cultural, thing
that you have to deal with as well.
Make sure that you're setting up
cross-functional collaboration teams.
That includes your development team,
your security, DevOps, your product teams.
Right.
The people that are engaged
with your customers
because you need to know
where the customer expectations are.
You need to understand
these sorts of things.
Make sure that you're doing postmortems,
that you're not finger pointing
to individuals,
but finger pointing to the problem.
Right? Go attack the problem.
Don't attack the
the individual's attack process attack.
Yeah.
You know, architecture,
not not individual people.
You get people to open up
more and talk about things
and have up hackathons
and, game days and things like that
where you take everyone say,
no one's developing right now.
We're all going to try and break
the system.
This this works really well, right?
And make sure that you set up
some governance and policies,
for experiments,
especially if you're doing,
anything with financial information, PPI,
or medical information, things
like that, you've got to make sure
that you're adhering to any of those rules
that that you have there.
Okay.
Measuring the impact.
Now this is another interesting thing
you all need to understand.
There's money involved in all this.
You can't architect things
and these big, huge experiments
in a silo because there's cost involved.
And this is where the trade off comes
with,
hey, if I don't do this,
what is the impact?
So this goes into risk management.
So you need to say my hypothesis is this.
This is what the impact
could be from my hypothesis.
And then figure out a way
that you can test this effectively
and efficiently
and if you get the okay to spend money
to do that, then that's great.
If you don't,
then come up with a different experiment,
come up with something better.
But you do need to,
you do need to
articulate what the impact is going to be
so that your risk management can decide,
whether it's worth it or not.
Right.
And this, this cost benefit thing
is something that a business has to weigh.
We can't just,
you know, go off and do things without
understanding the impact to the business.